<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unlavvfulnesse and danger of limited episcopacie· VVhereunto is subioyned a short reply to the modest advertiser and calme examinator of that treatise. As also the question of episcopacie discussed from Scripture and fathers. / By Robert Bailly pastor of Killwunning in Scotland.</title>
            <author>Baillie, Robert, 1599-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E174_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11030</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858927</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110987</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77490)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110987)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E174[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unlavvfulnesse and danger of limited episcopacie· VVhereunto is subioyned a short reply to the modest advertiser and calme examinator of that treatise. As also the question of episcopacie discussed from Scripture and fathers. / By Robert Bailly pastor of Killwunning in Scotland.</title>
                  <author>Baillie, Robert, 1599-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 2, 5-47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Vnderhill, at the Bible in Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Morley, George.  A modest advertisement concerning the present controversie about church-government.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Morley, George, 1597-1684. --  Modest advertisement concerning the present controversie about church-government.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110987:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110987:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VNLAVVFVLNESSE and danger of <hi>LIMITED</hi> EPISCOPACIE. VVhereunto is ſubioyned a ſhort reply to the Modeſt adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſer and calme examinator of that Treatiſe. AS ALSO <hi>The Queſtion of Epiſcopacie diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from Scripture and Fathers.</hi> BY Robert Bailly <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Killwunning <hi>in</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Vnderhill,</hi> at the Bible in Woodſtreet. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110987:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110987:2"/>
            <head>To the equitable Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome moneths ago there came out, from a learned and very judicious hand, a ſmall treatiſe to prove the unlawfulneſſe and danger of limited Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Shortly there after, there appeared in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this, a modeſt Advertiſement, and calme Examination, which was ſent enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a letter, from a Biſhop of prime place, to a Stationer for the preſſ, written whether by the Biſhop himſelfe, or a friend of his acquaintance, a Doctor of good eſteeme, I do not know. Some very few days after the
<pb facs="tcp:110987:3"/>firſt appearance of this anſwer, the reply following was readie, albeit till now it could not get the benefit of a preſſe. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Reply is not ſutable to the great worth of the firſt Treatiſe, but if it do ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently retund with cleere reaſon, all that the Anſwerer has oppoſed, it attains its end: of this performance be thou the judge, unto thy diſcretion I freely permit the pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the ſentence. I could wiſh from thy hands but one not very unreaſonable favour, that thou mightſt be pleaſed to call for, &amp; compare all the three Writs which are al but ſhort, that thou wouldſt lay toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in every paſſage, firſt, what the Authour did ſay, Secondly, what the Biſhop or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor does anſwer, and thirdly, what is here replied. This little labour will enable thee from due conſideration to make they equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table decree in the court of thy conſcience, according to which thou mayſt cheerfully proceed, firſt, to thy hearty deſires, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, as thy calling permits, to thy beſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, either for the holding up or pulling down this much agitate eſtate of Biſhops. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110987:3"/>
            <head>A Reply <hi>Unto the modeſt advertiſement and calme examination of the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and danger of limited EPISCOPACIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the multitude of rare novelties,
<note place="margin">It is much to ſee that Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall faction modeſt, and calme.</note> which of late have bin ſeen, Wee muſt take it for one not the leaſt, that Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall men have ſo far in writing changed their ſtile, as to meet their greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and extreame oppoſites, with no more, then modeſt advertiſements, and calme exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. God and the Parliament muſt be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that men may now diſpute, and diſcourſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Miters, without the hazard of ſtarving in a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110987:4"/>cloſe priſon, after the loſſe of eares, and ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matizing of cheeks upon the pillory. Who yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day did rage like Lyons, to day take upon them the skin of the meekeſt lambs.
<note n="*" place="margin">This modeſty is not ſincere.</note> If with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, the inward parts be truelie <hi>metamorphoſed,</hi> a ſhort time after the riſing of this Honourable Court will declare. For the preſent they muſt pardon the worlds misbelief of their total change while in the art of diſſembling they are yet ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, as to let appeare at the lands foot their old Leonine paw: for beſides that in the middeſt of your modeſtie you cannot forbeare the old Common place of calumnious railing againſt the verie well deſerving Saints of God, <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Knox,</hi> as uſurpers of greater authority over their brethren, then any Biſhop did ever in your knowledge aſſume in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. for my own part I ſhould be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſee any Biſhop in this land have ſuch authority over other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as <hi>Calvin</hi> had in <hi>Geneva,</hi> or <hi>Knox</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> Your very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whom you profeſſe to rencounter with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but calmenes and moderation, is traduced openly by you without any cauſe, as a bloudie man, as one who for the obteining of his conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the overthrow of Biſhops, threatens the ſhedding not of vulgar blood, but that of Princes, of their whol families, and no leſſe then the ruine of Kingdomes: You make him a Turkiſh <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 12. As for other argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that if wee admit not the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, there will be jealouſies between us, &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> that there will be changes, and periods of States, of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and Kingdomes, for theſe are inſinuate in this booke, and ſome are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to have ſaid that the Biſhops muſt down, or much bloud will be ſhed. Theſe we think not proofs but threatnings, and fitter for the mouth of a <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Derviſh,</hi> who plants Religion by the ſword, then for a Miniſter of the Goſpel of Chriſt.</note> rather then a Preacher of the Goſpel,
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pap.</hi> 18. I ſhall deſire the Authour to remember that there may be as much ambition in <hi>Corah,</hi> as in <hi>Aaron,</hi> and as much pride in refuſing to be governed, as in deſiring to govern, and to conſider whether theſe two ſpeeches are very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, that of his <hi>Pag</hi> 15 Is there none in the aſſembly fit to bee Preſident but one? and this of <hi>Corabs, Numb.</hi> 16. the Congregation is all holy, wherefore then lift yee up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord.</note> an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110987:4"/>ambitious <hi>Corah,</hi> a very Devill changed in an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of light:
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſid.</hi> And for the light whereof hee ſpeaks <hi>pag.</hi> 7. we deſire him not to bee too conſident, but rather that he will remember that of the Apoſtle, that Satan ſometimes changes himſelfe into an Angell of light, and cauſes that to be reverenced as an illumination, which many times is but an illuſion.</note> his arguments not onely to bee falſe, but Satanick illuſions. Behold, this is the calmneſſe of your examination, the meekeneſſe and moderation of your advertiſement.</p>
            <p>The greateſt part of your profeſſed vertue,
<note place="margin">Wherein their meekneſſe doth conſiſt.</note> we find to conſiſt in a key-coldnes, and well nigh mute-ſilence, when the hoteſt, and moſt pungent arguments approch your skin. Heere it is indeed, where the meeknes of your ſpirit, and unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſtrive, doth moſt appeare; for you are ever ſure, when any preſsing reaſon is brought, either altogether to let it go, as if you were ſtone-deafe, or if you take courage to contradict, your anſwers are ſo evidently impertinent, or triviall, and weak, that we might doubt whether this your oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were made in earneſt, or meerly for faſhion, unleſſe we did ſee it in the concluſion offered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the grave eie of the high Court of Parliament, before which no wiſe Man will adventure of purpoſe to trifle.</p>
            <p>Who ſo miſdoubts the equity of this our ſharpe cenſure, let him be onely pleaſed to fight with his own eies both the writs, comparing part with part, and every Argument with its anſwere,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110987:5"/>readily after this labour hee will ſubſcribe my Sentence: To facilitate the paines of any, who are deſirous to undertake this travell, I am content to go before in the way.</p>
            <p>The Authours Preface,
<note place="margin">To the Preface nothing is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered at all.</note> though ſhort, yet full of nervous conſiderations, it is your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to paſſe by without one ſyllable of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>After the Preface,
<note place="margin">And to the firſt principle no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</note> the Treatiſe it ſelfe begins with this propoſition; All the lawfull offices of the Church are appointed by God in his holy word: This ſerves both for a Major to the firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and a Principle for all the enſuing dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. The Authour proves his Principle by a number of cleere Scriptures, by many evident reaſons deduced from Scripture, and diverſe grounds of the moſt intelligent adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; what oppoſe you to all this? That the reader may not obſerve how you ſpeake to the point, you caſt up at the entry a quantity of duſt, to marre his ſight, you lay downe a Principle no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pertinent to the purpoſe: You propone a number of queſtions, which come not neere the Propoſition of your party, when at laſt you come to your anſwer, you will neither grant, nor deny, nor diſtinguiſh your adverſaries Propoſition, nor dare you oppoſe any thing to the manifold argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whereupon it is builded, onely you fall in before the time, and out of the due place up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hypotheſe of Epiſcopacie, and by way of contrary argumentation, with ſome old Popiſh flouriſhes of words, you inſinuate to the ſimple,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110987:5"/>rather then prove to any intelligent minde, that your Epiſcopacie, as an Apoſtolike inſtitution is to be embraced with a divine faith, no leſſe then the Creed, or the moſt holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>Your Principle is, That all would be carefull to keep the publike peace, as alſo,
<note place="margin">Your imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent principle concerns none but your ſelfe.</note> That no man for gain of things temporall, would loſe eternall: Your Falcon flight is here ſo high, your ſprings ſo far away, your conduit pipes ſo crooked, that he muſt have a skilled eye who can perceive the ways, how you bring home your waters, for any uſe to the purpoſe in hand. Doe you thinke that theſe who petition the Parliament, for rooting out of Epiſcopacie,
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 2. That men be not in their conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſo miſled either by ſome appearances of godlineſſe, and faire co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary zeale as thereby to hazard the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance of the common qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et.</note> which yet (as the whole Ile are now eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes) is the proper crime of your deareſt friends: for who elſe, to keepe upon their heads their tottering Mitres, did draw the King, and all his Dominions, to the very brink of the late de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate danger.</p>
            <p>The other halfe of your Principle, were very expedient to bee enlarged, and gravely applyed to theſe whom it concernes. You cannot bee ignorant who theſe men are, who theſe Yeeres paſt, upon no other grounds that can be conjectured, but only their own temporall advantages, and worldly feares, have betrayed the eternall truths of God. Who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110987:6"/>theſe are, who ſo long have ſate ſtill in a lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick quietneſſe, and yet cannot bee gotten awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to break off their dumbe ſilence, when <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſme,</hi> and all the heads of the <hi>Canterburian</hi> Popery, from ſo many Pulpits and Preſſes, have been over-ſpreading the whole Land.</p>
            <p>The queſtions which ſo ſeverely you urge to be anſwered,
<note place="margin">Your firſt queſtions an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> needed not to have been at all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned. Anent your firſt, ſuppone we grant that ſalvation may be obtained under Epiſcopacie, what then, will this inferre that Biſhops neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily muſt be retained, and that their rooting out is needleſſe? All your friends confeſſe, that under the Pope, and Cardinals, ſalvation may be by all, and is by the moſt, obtained: Will you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude, that the ejection of the Pope, and Cardinals out of <hi>England,</hi> was a needleſſe work? Your friends do ſo indeed,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Ladenſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: c. 3.</note> And ſo your Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopall principles force them, but I hope the Parliament, to whom you ſubmit your Treatiſe, will be loth in haſte by your perſwaſion to bring back the Pope, and Cardinals Authoritie.</p>
            <p>How many good works your Biſhops have forced men to omit, and how many evill to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, ſearch the Regiſters of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and you ſhall want no ſtore.</p>
            <p>Shall the Reformers be in great darkneſſe, and the Martyrs miſerable, if in their days there was in the Church any thing, which they were not able to amend, or which came not in their minde to complain of? Did any Martyr of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110987:6"/>Church ever die in the quarrell of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, or Ceremonies? Did their perſecutors require them to ſeale any of theſe things with their bloud? Was it any diſgrace to theſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> rectified many things in King <hi>Edwards</hi> Liturgie, and went beyond that Reformation which in their dayes was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained?</p>
            <p>Your ſecond queſtions are not unlike the firſt,
<note place="margin">Alſo your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</note> for their pertinencie. All the Reformed World is fully agreed to have Epiſcopacie overthrown, onely ſome few of the Engliſh Church, for their own intereſt do oppoſe. There is as great an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony among all in ſetting up of Presbyteries, and Synods, as in caſting out the old rubbiſh of Biſhops and their Courts; If ſome few of the Engliſh be ſcrupulous about the limits, bounds, and extent of the power of Synods, It is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, Epiſcopall tyranny has bred, and foſtered more Schiſmes in <hi>England,</hi> then have been heard of in all the Reformed Churches beſide; If this fountain of Schiſme were once well ſtopped, We make no queſtion, but as in <hi>Scotland, Holland, France, Swize, Geneva,</hi> and many places in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> there is no diſcord, ſo like wayes in <hi>England,</hi> one or two well governed generall Aſſemblies would amicably put an end to all the queſtions that are, or need to be moved about the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, or any thing elſe whatſoever.</p>
            <p>What you enquire further, of the divine right of Presbyterie, of the places of Scripture
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110987:7"/>brought to prove it, of the ſenſe, and conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Scriptures. In all reaſon you are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to heare with us great Patience avow that the Scripttures we bring, do infer neceſſarily, and cleerly our Concuſion, till you brought ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall anſwer to the contrary.</p>
            <p>The laſt of your Queſtions,
<note place="margin">Your laſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</note> is but a flaſh of your Rhetorick faculty of exaggeration, your ſelf muſt make anſwer to it; for you do ſay that God diſcharges under pain of damnation all that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, and that every thing is unlawfull which is againſt the Word of God: That Presbyters, by the Word of God, have the power of laying on the hands, and of uſing the keyes, you will ſhortly grant; that therefore an Epiſcopacie ſhould be permitted, to ſpoile theſe Presbyters of the priviledges which God in his word has granted unto them, or to uſurpe unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and devolve on their Officials, the Rites of the inferiour Clergie, you dare not deny to be a wrong which deſerves amending.</p>
            <p>At laſt you come to the purpoſe,
<note place="margin">The Authors principle left unbrauled.</note> the Authours Principle, but you finde it ſo hote, that you dare not ſtand long upon it.</p>
            <p>You tell us firſt, that the Authours diſcourſe upon this Principle is written with much art, and eloquence, for inſinuation with the unwary Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Who pleaſeth to read the writ it ſelfe, ſhall ſee, that all the art of the Authour is in a very plain diſcourſe to couch, ſo briefly as is poſſible, a number of cleere and ſtrong probations, for to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110987:7"/>convince the mind of all attentive Readers.</p>
            <p>Againe, you tell us that the Principle may be granted. Why do you mutter betwixt your teeth? ſpeak out cleerly, and plainly, for if you grant it, your cauſe is loſt, if you deny it, your next will be to anſwer the numerous arguments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is compaſſed, not any one whereof you are bold to try.</p>
            <p>In the third place, that you may leave a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne for eſcaping, the Authors cleere and plaine principle, That no office is lawful in Gods houſe, which Chriſt has not appointed, you transforme in an other mold, to wit, That none may admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Word or Sacraments, impoſe hands, or uſe the keyes, but ſuch as Chriſt has appointed; When thus you have taken leave to corrupt, not the words only, but the matter of your adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries very principle,
<note place="margin">Epiſcopall Courts ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledged to be unlawfull</note> Notwithſtanding you ſee the Concluſion that flows from your owne propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to wit, that your high Commiſsioners, your Chancellours, and all the Rabble of your Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Courtiours doe meddle with Church cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures contrary to Chriſts appointment; This you do not deny, but beare us in hand that theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions may be amended without noiſe, or ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall. It were good that your friends in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation would preveen the honourable Houſe of Commons, that at laſt they would offer of free accord to paſſe from theſe long defended oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Courts, before with greater noiſe and ſhame they be compelled to render to the Presbyterie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110987:8"/>theſe Rites, whereof too long it has been diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by your Biſhops fraud and force.</p>
            <p>When you have broken in unſeaſonably upon the <hi>Hypotheſe</hi> of Epiſcopacie, how marvellouſly doe you ſhift, and extenuate the queſtion? The authors principle did ſpeak expreſly, and ſoly, of a diſtinct office in the Church of God: you dare not ſay whether Epiſcopacie be any ſuch thing or not, All the diſtinction betwixt a Biſhop and a Presbyter that you ſpeak of, is a higher, and lower degree, as it were of the ſame office: Your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren will give you ſmall thanks for this extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for you know they maintaine Epiſcopacie to be a true, and diſtinct office from the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, unto the which, beſide a Superioritie of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, the diſtinct faculty or power of Ordination, and Juriſdiction, eſſentially doth belong, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſimple prieſts, <hi>qua tales,</hi> have nought at all to doe.</p>
            <p>Beſide, the Authors principle, and the probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof, conclude all that you here doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, for they inferre the unlawfulneſſe of any majoritie of one Church Officer over another, without Chriſts appointment, from ſo cleere texts of Scripture, and ſo ſound grounds of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controverted Divinity, as you find not your ſelfe diſpoſed to anſwer any one of them.</p>
            <p>While as you require proof in that place, for all the other parts of our Diſcipline, you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable. When you have given ſatisfactorie anſwers to all that is brought in the head of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110987:8"/>it will be then time, and no ſooner, to proceed unto other Articles, which ſo long as Epiſcopacy ſtands, were needleſſe to be ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>In your contrary argumentations you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to prove a very ſtrange concluſion,
<note place="margin">Your great words extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie are full of vanitie.</note> That the order of Biſhops is no leſſe Apoſtolicall, then the very Creed, and to be received with no leſſe faith then the very Scriptures, yea, with much more, as it ſeems you import; for you equal the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Biſhops in this, that both are alike uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, and unqueſtioned traditions: but in this you ſeeme to give Biſhops a ſurer ground then you grant to Scriptures, for the ground where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon you here, and many of your fellowes elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where embrace the Scriptures, is ſole Tradition, but the grounds whereupon you receive the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Biſhops, is not ſole tradition; <hi>but ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry paſsages of Scripture alſo as you alleage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This your mighty Concluſion you prove not by any argument, but onely by a number of big words borrowed from the Papiſts, in this ſame and many more ſubjects. You tell us that many Scriptures are alleaged for Epiſcopacy, and that theſe Scriptures are exponed in your ſenſe by all the Fathers, yea, by all Writers for fifteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres. I hope that your ſelfe will finde it reaſon that wee be permitted to take your great words for nought, but vaine ecchoes in the Aire, while you be pleaſed to produce at leaſt ſome one Scripture, ſome one Father, ſome one Writer,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110987:9"/>which here you have not done. Alſo while you would have us taking it on your naked word, that all times, all places, all perſons are for Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and that for ſuch Biſhops as you here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſlie deſcribe, to whom alone it belongs to rule, as it is proper for the inferiour Presbyters to be ruled, ſuffer us to ſay that you are greatly miſtaken, till wee have heard ſome one of your proofs. Your patience will here I hope be the greater, when you read in the ſubſequent writt for this our contradiction more Scriptures and Fathers then you in haſte are like ſatisfactorily to anſwere.
<note place="margin">The queſtion of Epiſcopacie diſcuſt.</note> In that ſame ſhort writ you will ſee all the Scriptures, and the moſt pregnant paſſages of antiquity which the beſt learned on your ſide are accuſtomed to produce, anſwered by the ancients themſelves ſo cleerely, that while you give ſome evidence to the contrarie, Indifferent men will pronounce, that wee have but too good reaſon to avow Epiſcopacie as your ſelfe in the ſame place deſcribes it, to be a plant which God never ſet in his garden, to bee a meere ſtranger to the ancient Church for ſome hundred yeeres, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver while the Pope had uſurped mainly by the help of his Epiſcopall juriſdiction, many Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian priviledges.</p>
            <p>Your conſequences, beſides the palpable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of your Antecedent, are weake, vitious, and inconſequent; though your Epiſcopacie be an Antichriſtian errour, yet it will not follow that all people who are ſubject to it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110987:9"/>as Antichriſtian, and falſe worſhipers of God; for you know that one fault and one quality is not ſufficient to put on the ſubject an abſolute denomination. What you adde of the fountaine and originall of Presbyteries, it ſhews, if not your ignorance, yet your great forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not onely what <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and other of the ancients have written of the Presbyteries in their times, but alſo what your ſelfe within a few pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges does write of Presbyteries which you could admit, though with an Epiſcopall Moderator.</p>
            <p>This is the matter of your firſt ſix pages,
<note place="margin">To the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument the anſwer is Popiſh and nought.</note> upon the Authours Principle; when you come to his Arguments, your Anſweres are ſhorter, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better. The firſt Argument, That theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, which of purpoſe, and moſt punctually ſet downe the offices of Gods houſe, eſpeciallie the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, and the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> ſpeak not at all of your Biſhops. You firſt deny the Argument, albeit in your deniall you are ſo rationall, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to give any reaſon for what you ſay, nor to anſwere any of the proofes whereby the Author confirmed his aſſertion, Then you deny the ground whereupon the argument is builded, The Principle which before in the proper place you durſt not deny, but rather did inſinuate your granting of it; however the Authours Probation of that Principle ſtands as yet untouched.</p>
            <p>While you tell us here that Tradition is a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ground for Epiſcopacie though Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110987:10"/>were lacking, you but joine with your Brethren the Canterburians, who upon this ground preſſe upon us already their Altars, Croſſes, Images, the primacie of the Pope, and much more, and ſhew their minde by this doore to let in upon us the whole flood of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian abominations, when they find their ſeaſon, eſpecially as your ſelf here does profeſſe, any matter of practice, of diſcipline, of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This your popiſh errour of tradition is a very generall, and catholike one, which ſhakes not one or two but all the ground-ſtones of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant reformations.</p>
            <p>The Authours ſecond Argument is,
<note place="margin">The ſecond you anſwere by a nonſenſe and childiſh toy.</note> That no inferiour officer in the new teſtament, carries the name of any ſuperiour; but ſo it is that a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter every where carries the name of a Biſhop; Therefore a Presbyter is not an inferiour officer to a Biſhop. What here you bring, is ſo far from the ſhew of any anſwere, that it is like you have not conceived the drift of the Argument, only the non ſenſe of your reply is compenſed with your extraordinary quickneſſe, to take your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarie twice in his own argument, in his owne net, firſt you will put him to a <hi>non plus</hi> by an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatory, where then are ruling Elders by their names diſtinguiſhed? you have read I believe the 1. <hi>Timothy</hi> 5.17. there you may ſee ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders, by their name, and ſurname, cleerly diſtinguiſhed from Preachers of the word; you know alſo that there are a number of paſſages of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110987:10"/>the Fathers for theſe ruling Elders in the booke of <hi>Gerſombucerus,</hi> which the boldeſt of your party for all their big words and exclamations in the eares of ſilly people, durſt never yet after twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two yeeres adviſement ſo much as offer to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
            <p>Thereafter you triumph as if you had drawn from your Adverſaries own pen, by an ocular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtration, the ful proof of your whol co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion. The ſuperiority of a Biſhop to a Presbyter by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right, becauſe forſooth the author ſays, That Biſhop and Paſtor which are all one, are made by the Apoſtle ſuperiour to a Presbyter. Wee did not believe that any man of the leaſt acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with theſe controverſies, had beene igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of that common, and triviall homonomie of the word Presbyter, and Elder, ſometimes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a preaching Elder, ſometimes for a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elder, and ſometimes for both. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor with the Scriptures makes, a Paſtor, a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, a preaching elder, to be altogether one, and in nothing to differ, but as three ſynonimous names of one, and the ſame officer, which by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right is indeed ſuperiour to a ruling Elder, or Preſbyter, this no man ever did queſtion, but no way ſuperiour to a preaching Elder, of whom alone is all the preſent queſtion.</p>
            <p>The Authors third and fourth Argument con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed ſtrongly by a number of pregnant Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are all utterly miſpent,
<note place="margin">To the third and fourth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument no ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere appears.</note> and not one word of anſwere made to either of them.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:110987:11"/>
            <p>His fifth Argument,
<note place="margin">The fifth is in ſhew granted.</note> That by Chriſts inſtitution &amp; the conſtant practice of the Apoſtles, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of ordination, and juriſdiction, is never commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to one Biſhop, but ever to a number of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and others, as is cleared, by a multitude of manifeſt Scriptures. This you cannot deny, yet your heart will not permit you freely to grant it. You are content that in ordination, and juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Biſhops ſhould be aſsiſted by Presbyters, but the argument infers much more, to wit that your Biſhops in uſurping to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelvs the power of juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, &amp; transferring of it to their carnal courts, that their aſſuming by vertue of their office the power of ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though for the form they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſome Presbyters to be their aſsiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in giving of orders, that both theſe faculties which make not the abuſe but the two main limbs, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grall parts of the office it ſelfe, are wicked pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices againſt Chriſts ordinance, not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but preſently aboliſhed, with a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, that with a high hand for ſo long a time theſe tyrannous uſurpations have bin maintained.</p>
            <p>The ſixt Argument was from the 22.
<note place="margin">The ſixt is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 25. where Chriſt forbids all Paſtors to accept any Majority or preheminence over their brethren, This the Author proves from Scripture, Reaſon, and Antiquitie, to evert the office of Biſhops. All that you anſwere is that this place does not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the Apoſtles to accept any degree of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour above their brethren wherein they may go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them for their profit, It follows then that by this place Biſhops are not hindered to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110987:11"/>as great authority over the Church as the greateſt Emperours ever had over the bodies, or Chriſt himſelfe as you confeſſe here over the ſoules of men.</p>
            <p>Having evinced the unlawfulneſſe of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie it ſelfe by the former Arguments,
<note place="margin">The Authors firſt reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacie is but ſlighted.</note> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing enervate by all your Oppoſition, in the reſt of the treatiſe the Author reaſons againſt the lawfulneſſe of the leaſt degrees, and beſt limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that evill; his firſt argument is well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with Scripture, and reaſon, you anſwere but to one piece, caſting by the firſt, and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt parts of it, to wit, all parts, all degrees, all meanes, all appearances of the diſcharged evill; you had good reaſon to cut off all theſe portions from the Argument, for you ſaw that your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction was not applicable to theſe, for you will be loath to deny that Epiſcopacie, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever limitate, is ſome degree, ſome part, ſome mean, ſome appearance, not by accident, but of its own nature, of that Epiſcopacie which now ſtands in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The part of the Argument which you take in hand is not ſufficiently anſwered, for you clear your diſtinction with no more then your own ſimple aſſertion, That limited Epiſcopacie is not in it ſelfe, but alone by Satans malice, either a cauſe, or a beginning, or a provocation to Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie as now it ſtands; Surely that effect which has followed limited Epiſcopacie, in all places where ever it has dwelt, may not well be denyed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110987:12"/>to be naturall unto it, however you dare not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your diſtinction, for it will ſound harſhlie in the eares of your Neighbours, that limited Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie ſhould be a beginning, &amp; a provocation, by the malice and craft of the Devill, of that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacie which now in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>England</hi> has place.</p>
            <p>The Author in the next place by cleer Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures does prove,
<note place="margin">The ſecond is unwittingly granted.</note> That the reformation of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacie muſt be taken, not from the times of the poſteriour Fathers, but from the beginning, the dayes of Chriſt, and the Apoſtles; your anſwere is ſhort, but how good, your ſelfe be judge. You grant the Argument in all things which have a divine patterne; but that Presbyteriall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſuch, you deny: you remember that the queſtion here is alone of Epiſcopacie, what ſay you of its patterne? if its patterne be not divine you have loſt your labour; If it bee divine, then according to your ſelfe it muſt bee conformed to the firſt, and Apoſtolicall times. As for Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Government which placeth the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Ordination and Juriſdiction, never in one, but in a multitude of Presbyters, that the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne thereof is Scripturall, and divine, your ſelfe before durſt not contradict.</p>
            <p>While you make it the Authors tenet, that all the fathers, and all Chriſtians, in all ages throughout the world, have agreed to bring forth Antichriſt, wee acknowledg a tract of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed modeſtie, for the furtheſt the Author ſayes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110987:12"/>is that many of the fathers did unwittingly bring forth the Antichriſt, and that the lights of the Proteſtant Churches, at, and ſince the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, have diſcovered many ſecrets concerning the Antichriſt, which were not knowne in former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; that you have not faith to believe this, Wee doe not marvail, for this is one of the heads a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many more, wherein you of the faction, long ago have made Apoſtacie from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and all the reformed Churches; So far are your brethren from denying the Popes Antichriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, that they avow his holineſſe this day to be a true and lawfull Biſhop, the firſt Patriarch of the Chriſtian world, from whoſe See of <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> derive their ſucceſsion, and to whom in reaſon all Biſhops where ever they live, ought ſubjection, and canonicall obedience.</p>
            <p>In the third place the Author caſts together a number of grave conſiderations againſt all degrees of Epiſcopacie,
<note place="margin">The third alſo but ſlighted.</note> almoſt in every ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is couched a pithy Argument. In your anſwers you are in ſuch haſte, that you caſt all behind your Back, you aſcribe to him that he did not write, that Popery and Prelacy are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; This your own conceit you refute, but of all your partie hath ſaid, you take notice of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſave one word, that Prelacie is a ſtep to Poperie; Sundry reaſons are brought by the Author to prove this, all which you misken, only you argue to the contrarie, that the ſuppreſsing of Epiſcopacie is the way for ſupporting of Popery
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110987:13"/>and introducting Anarchie. Upon this laſt you run out in a large diſcourſe; for this is the field wherein you of the faction are wont to expatiate with greateſt delight.</p>
            <p>You prove your firſt point by a cleer miſtake,
<note place="margin">All Papiſts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacie.</note> diſtinguiſh the Accident from the Subject, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie from Biſhops, you will finde that neither the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> nor any Popiſh Divine are for ſuppreſſing of Epiſcopacie; This office to the uttermoſt of their power they all uphold, neither have you or any of your brethren any one argument for that office, which is not bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from them: It is true that the moſt of the Papalines doe ſuppreſſe other Biſhops, to make great their Pope, but the meanes whereby they put under the Popes feet both Biſhops, Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and all, both Clergie, and Laity, is chiefly this unhappie inſtrument of Epiſcopacie, which in the Popes perſon they advance to the higheſt degree of its extenſion, and this is nothing leſſe then true Antichriſtianiſme. If you have read <hi>Padre Paulo's</hi> Hiſtory of that Councel you name, you muſt ſubſcribe what I have ſaid.</p>
            <p>That from the removall of Epiſcopacie,
<note place="margin">The putting downe of the Biſhops would bring to an end the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and ſchiſmes.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and anarchie does follow, you would have the Divines of <hi>New England</hi> to prove by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors principles. The manifold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions which you aſcribe to theſe Divines, whether they will own them or not, themſelves doe know, with their tenets I am not well acquainted, onely it ſeemes nothing marvelous, if Epiſcopall cruelty
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110987:13"/>baniſhing them to the Wilderneſſe of a new World, ſhould have driven them to greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies then any you name, but were they once freed of all feare of that monſter Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and brought back to their Countrey, where in libertie and peace they might enjoy in a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall aſſembly, the benefit of a leaſurely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with their brethren, wee make little doubt of their acquieſcing to the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the reſt of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p>As for theſe grounds, you make the Author lay for them, you are no more happie here then in the reſt of your writ; For this is your Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm. Whatſoever God has not eſtabliſhed in his Church, is unlawful; but God has not eſtabliſhed that ſome paſtors ſhould be over others; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is unlawfull: What a poore caption is in your <hi>minor</hi> in the word <hi>Some</hi> taken for one only, or for more, for one Biſhop, or for more Paſtors, &amp; Elders conveened in a Synod or Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery? That any one ſhould rule over the reſt, the Author has proved it to bee againſt the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God; That a Presbytery and Synod of many ſhould be over every one particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when ever it ſhall be challenged, it may be eaſily proved to be according to holy Scripture and all good reaſon.</p>
            <p>What you ſubjoine about the State of the queſtion, though it be not very tymous in the end of your diſpute, yet wee ſhall conſider
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110987:14"/>it ſince you ſo requeſt. You ſay that the ſtate of the queſtion is not whether a Biſhop in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times had a Presbyterie under him, This you dare not deny unto us, for you know too wel, and all that have looked upon any of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, muſt confeſſe that a Biſhop without a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie was a ſtrange Monſter in the primitive times, and a plain <hi>non ens</hi> not to be found in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeeres in the Chriſtian World. But withall you may not deny the impudent oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your Biſhops in <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">You muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence of the Biſhops.</note> Their oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in that (as they have learned alone from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Biſhops in the late moſt corrupt times) they have aboliſhed the ancient Presbyteries, It is true that ſome of them now, when they are like to be compelled to live a little in order, begin to ſhew their contentment to have ſet up again in all the Kingdome theſe Presbyteries, but who of them all before this time were ever heard to ſpeake one word of reſtoring the Church to the uſe of Presbyteriall government, which now they dare not deny to be her due by right both divine and alſo Eccleſiaſtick, in all the ancient times of any puritie. Their impudence that hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they have had faces and browes to beare the King and State in hand, that their Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Government without Presbyteries was according to the Practice of the ancient Church, that Antiquity, Univerſality, and what not, was for them, when yet the leaſt twitch of triall muſt extort from them a cleere confeſsion, That the chief ſinews of that government which was uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110987:14"/>in the ancient Church, was ſeated in the body of Presbyteries, the very name whereof till the ſitting down of this Parlament all of you did abhorre, <hi>cane pejus, et angue.</hi> If there remain any drop of ingenuous blood, you would proclaim openly, and no more mutter within your teeth, that your late injurious errour, and without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay your ſelfe be the firſt, and moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Solicitor of the Parlament, for the re-erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all the Kingdome of theſe Presbyteries, which now at laſt you confeſſe were univerſally in uſe in all the purer times of antiquity.</p>
            <p>As for that which you deſire to bee the State of the queſtion,
<note place="margin">Engliſh Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacie is a late corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a meere ſtranger to the ancient Church.</note> whether ever there was a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery without a Biſhop over it, you will I hope bee content after the faſhion of reaſonable men to ſpeake of things not of names, you will make no queſtion with us about the name of Biſhops, which wee never deny to be frequent, both in Scripture, and antiquity, But the thing ſignified by this name, An officer, as all your partie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes him, who in his Dioceſſe hath the power of Ordination, and Juriſdiction, by vertue of his office, This is the ſubject of all our queſtion. You affirme that in the ancient times Biſhops in this Senſe were ſet over Presbyteries, Wee do deny. We ſhould be glad to ſee your Affirmation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that ever there was in the Church of God any ſuch Biſhops before the Pope had brought his Biſhoprick to the Cope-ſtone of Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme; Our negative wee have laboured to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110987:15"/>prove in the following treatiſe, by more paſſages of antiquity then you will have leaſure in haſte to anſwere.</p>
            <p>As for the Biſhops of the ancient Church which agree with yours onely in the naked name, but in the eſſentiall parts of the office doe differ as much as the Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> this day from the Duke of <hi>Muſcovie,</hi> as the Emperours of <hi>Rome</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Seneca</hi> from the old <hi>Imperatores</hi> in the time of the Common-wealth: The queſtion about them will bee whether their right in theſe ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t times was divine, or human, whether they ſtood by Apoſtolick tradition, or alone by Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall conſtitution eſtabliſhed at the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches pleaſure, and ſo by her free will removea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. You will be a better diſputer then any of your ſide who yet have appeared if you can make good the firſt, yea that you can prove the ſecond to have been univerſal, we do not believe. If every Church would ſearch their originall rights, as they of <hi>Scotland</hi> have done their own, readily as theſe have found their Church in the moſt ancient times governed by Presbyters without any biſhops at all, ſo much as in name, for ſome hundred yeers, ſo many other natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Churches might finde the ſame upon the like diligence of tryall; however when it comes to the exacteſt ſearch, it will appeare that Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie was at moſt but an humane Eccleſiaſtick conſtitution, neither more ancient, more univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, nor received upon any better grounds then
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110987:15"/>the Primacie of the Patriarch of <hi>Rome,</hi> then the manifold fraternities of the Monkes, Fryers, and Nunnes, Theſe, though according to your friends aſſertion, ſo anciently, ſo univerſally, ſo piouſly eſtabliſhed, that all the reformed, and <hi>England</hi> among the reſt, are much to be blamed both for their firſt raſhneſſe to reject, and there too long lingring ſince to reſtore them, yet as <hi>England</hi> did never repent the caſting out of the former, according to the example of her ſiſters abroad, ſo now wee believe, if ſhee may be pleaſed to follow the ſame example in caſting out the other ſhee ſhall have as little cauſe of ſorrow.</p>
            <p>The Author did ſhew at length the vanity of their expectation who deceive themſelves with hopes to get Biſhops kept in order by the bonds of any imaginable limitations:
<note place="margin">No caveats are able to keepe Biſhops long in order.</note> for the demonſtration hereof, he ſets downe the caveats, whereby the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Kirke and Kingdome did bind their Biſhops, then which <hi>England</hi> can not invent harder this day for theirs. The knot can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be faſter tied. The <hi>Scots</hi> had their Biſhops conſent, ſubſcription, and ſolemn oath, The King in perſon in the generall Aſſembly did ratifie the bargaine, numbers of Parliaments did eſtabliſh the liberties of Presbyteries. Sundry reaſons the Authour brings to cleer that <hi>England</hi> is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at this time to employ ſuch meanes to keepe their Biſhops low, as <hi>Scotland</hi> then did uſe, your anſwere to all is compendious: you ſay that all your adverſaries arguments are weake, but how
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110987:16"/>your ſaying may be proved, you take not time to tell us.</p>
            <p>The Author in the end of his writ makes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to a number of the common jargous of Prelaticall men,
<note place="margin">Presbyteriall government a heavier ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to ſchiſme then Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall.</note> eſpecially that of Schiſme in the Church, and danger to the State, which by the removall of Epiſcopacie, they take upon them to propheſie, will certainly fall out: To both theſe Objections hee gives a number of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſatisfactory and grave replies. In your anſwer you misken well neere them all, Theſe few you picke out are caſt in a ſtrange confuſion here and there in your Papers.</p>
            <p>Againſt his replies to the firſt objection of Schiſme, you rejoinder that the diviſions of <hi>New England</hi> are witneſſes of theſe Schiſmes which proceed from the want of Epiſcopacie: you do well to ſpeake to us of men in an other World, with whoſe eſtate we are not acquainted, but can you ſay that there are half ſo many Schiſmes in <hi>New England</hi> where Biſhops are not, as we ſee in <hi>Old England</hi> where Biſhops are in their full Strength. Speak of the things we know, Behold the Churches of <hi>Europe,</hi> from whence Biſhops are baniſhed, <hi>Scotland, France, Holland, Swize, Geneva, &amp;c.</hi> Did you ever heare of any either Schiſme or Hereſie, in theſe places, except when Presbyteriall government was ſuppreſſed? did that diſcipline any ſooner get leave to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy its native ſtrength, but in a ſhort time it made the Countries where it dwelt free of all theſe evills</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:110987:16"/>
            <p>It is made evident in the next place,
<note place="margin">If Biſhops ſtand ſchiſme in <hi>England</hi> muſt increaſe.</note> that the keeping of Epiſcopacie on foot any longer, in all probability will fill the Church of <hi>England</hi> with many pitifull diviſions, both amongſt themſelves at home, and from all their Neighbours abroad; concerning the reformed Churches over ſea you anſwer, that in time bigon you have kept good correſpondence with them, notwithſtanding of all the difference in diſcipline; but truly the correſpondence you ſpeake of is to be aſcribed much rather to the patience and long ſuffering of your good Neighbours, then to any well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of your Biſhops: for their doctrine in the point of Epiſcopacie, is cleerly Schiſmaticall, as you may ſee in the Pedagogick, and Maſter <hi>Likes</hi> Letter of <hi>Andrews</hi> to <hi>Muleine,</hi> and in other of your Prelaticall writs, where your men with the Papiſts, by all the arguments they can invent, do preſſe the Reformed Churches to embrace their Epiſcopacie as an Apoſtolike inſtitution, the want whereof puts them from the very being of a Church, &amp; makes the calling of their Preachers to be unlawfull, without any right. This wound, I grant your Biſhops, when they have given it, go about incontinent to cure, but in vaine, for if their ground of Epiſcopacies divine right hold, it is not poſſible to defend the calling of theſe Miniſters who refuſe Epiſcopall Ordination.</p>
            <p>While here you prefer for number, and equall both for learning and pietie, the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to all the reſt of the Reformed, we doe not marvell, ſince you contemne them both ſo farre,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110987:17"/>that when they are joined together, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and the <hi>Grecian</hi> which follows the <hi>Roman</hi> in the moſt of her er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Idolatries, to be but a few perſons in the Weſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> not comparable with all the Chriſtians, as you ſpeake <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. upon the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>You profeſſe at laſt, it is a ſmall thing to you, to differ from all the Reformed, when you joine with the ancient Kirke in the firſt three hundred Yeeres; we have ſhewn before the vanitie of this Language, for in Epiſcopall Government, you differ little leſſe from the ancient Kirke, then from the Reformed, of whom yee were ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the ancient Presbyterie is a ſtranger to your Land, and your Epiſcopacie would be as great a ſtranger in any Chriſtian Kirke, for the firſt five hundred Yeers, as the drink of <hi>Muſcovia</hi> would be this day in <hi>Venice,</hi> or the Empire of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> in the days of <hi>Cato</hi> the elder.</p>
            <p>The Authour named the jealouſies that would be inavoidable betwixt the two Kirks of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> if Epiſcopacie, which the one, with the King, and all the Worlds conſent hath caſt downe, ſhould by the other bee kept on foot; upon this paſſage you fall once and again, at the firſt time, that you may have a larger ſcope for a tract of your modeſtie, you draw a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from another farre diſtant place of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours writ, where hee ſayes no more, but that vices contrarie to pietie, righteouſneſſe, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, where they doe raign, are certaine fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110987:17"/>and cauſes of many calamities, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and changes of States, Kingdomes, and Families. This you cut out from its own place, and joine with the fore-named ſentence, that from both you may make out your verie modeſt concluſion, that your author, more like a <hi>Turkiſh Darviſe,</hi> then a Miniſter of the Goſpel, does threaten to overthrow Biſhops, by the bloudie Sword, by the change of States, Families, and Kingdomes, and that not the author alone, but alſo all the Presbyterians, yea, the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall government it ſelf, is guiltie of perſecuting the perſons, and tyrannouſly preſſing the ſouls of men, no leſſe then the papiſts; if this be your ſtile when your mood is calme, how crabbed muſt your dialect be when you are commoved?</p>
            <p>When in your roving you fall the ſecond time upon this ſame point, you anſwer ſomwhat more pertinently then is your cuſtome, That you truſt the <hi>Scots</hi> will count it as unreaſonable to have their diſcipline preſſed upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as they did eſteem it, to have the <hi>Engliſh</hi> preſſed upon them; but I pray you, what if the <hi>Scots</hi> ſhould leave here their own way, and follow your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, might any of you in reaſon complaine of ſuch a retaliation? Did ever your Biſhops give over to force upon the <hi>Scots</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with all their might, till the whole Iſle was in armes, and in the midſt of a dangerous war? Left they ever their deſigne, till God, the King, and the Parliament, made them unable for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110987:18"/>proſecution thereof. It is like that the <hi>Scots</hi> will be loth to follow that your example; Yet certainly, they have all the reaſon of the World to perſwade with all their power, their Brethren of <hi>England</hi> to joine with them, and all the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med everie where, to batter downe that unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Epiſcopacie, without any reſting, till the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Biſhop, the Antichriſt himſelf, from whom the Prelates of <hi>England</hi> confeſſe they draw the line of their pedigree be overthrowne, and quite aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>If in this no leſſe noble then neceſſary enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe the Engliſh will bee lacking to themſelves, in this ſeaſon of ſo golden an occaſion, the Scottiſh cannot faile to regiſter for the poſterity a Proteſtation of their great and too well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded feares, that Epiſcopacie in <hi>England</hi> may well change the habit, but never the nature, that as it has beene ever ſince the Reformation a bitter fountain of almoſt all the troubles that hath vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Scotiſh Kirk, ſo it ſhall remain like it ſelf a Spring of future woes to the Churches of the whole Iſle.</p>
            <p>The domeſtike diviſions which are like to encreaſe amongſt the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> if that root wee ſpeak of be not drawne up, and caſt over Sea towards <hi>Rome</hi> whence it came, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor expreſſeth them cleerely; all that you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is a ſalt gybe; it is truly ſtrange if any ſhould make queſtion that as to this day many of the moſt Godly in <hi>England</hi> who have been far from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110987:18"/>reſiſting authority in any thing, yet could never follow the Doctrine of the Biſhops ſo far, as with them to believe that the ſentence of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, whether Civill or Eccleſiaſticke, was a ſufficient argument to perſwade their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that Biſhops were a holy ordinance, ſo hereafter that many more who walk moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully according to the rule of Gods law, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſubmit their hearts to the government of Biſhops, though after the loſſe of their cares, their Heads ſhould be chopped off from their ſhoulders.</p>
            <p>The Authour in his Anſwer to the ſecond or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie Objection, anent the danger of change,
<note place="margin">No hazard to the State in changing the preſent go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church.</note> propones a number of very wiſe conſiderations, whereby he makes it evident, that presbyteriall Government will much better accord with the eſtate of <hi>England,</hi> then Epiſcopall; all theſe you paſſe by in your anſwer, only you ſnatch at a word or two, in ſome few of them. The Author upon preſuppoſition of his firſt principle, that no Office might be permitted in the Houſe of God, without his own appointment, inferreth, that as a man would be loth to ſuffer any of his ſervants to place in his houſe Governours beſide his own knowledge: ſo that Chriſt will not be content when any does erect in his Church, Biſhops to be guides, which hee did never ordain.</p>
            <p>You touch not the point while yee tell us, that a Wiſeman would never permit a Democratie to be erected in his Family, and ſo that none
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110987:19"/>would ſet up a Presbyterie in the Church; a Presbyterie is not a Democracie, but be what ever it may, the reaſon here proceeds alone from the authoritie of a Maſter, to plant in his owne houſe what Government he will, without liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for ſervants to diſpute the qualitie thereof.</p>
            <p>In the current of his Diſcourſe,
<note place="margin">You ſnatch at ſome few of the Authours words, but let paſſe without anſwer, the moſt of his matter.</note> amongſt other interrogations, the authour did queſtion, if in a whole Synod there was none meet to preſede, but only one perpetually: For it is well known that in every dioces there is a number much mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for any good ſervice then the Biſhop. Of this harmleſſe queſtion you make a great quarrell, and compare the authour to <hi>Cora,</hi> your ſelfe to <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his interrogation to the rebellious ſpeeches of that wicked man, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>When the whole has ſufficiently overthrown all the matter of Epiſcopacie, whether abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute or limitate, hee bringeth ſundry arguments, why the verie name of a Biſhop would not be retained, but you are not pleaſed to take notice of any one of them.</p>
            <p>In the laſt two pages, verie cleerlie by divers evidences, he declareth the great and rare oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie which God hath put in the hand of this preſent Parliament to remove the whole root of Epiſcopacie, with as great eaſe, as to cut off its branches; all this you misken, only to give us a further taſte of the temper of your modeſt Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, you inſinuate, <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. that the greateſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie you can remark in this ſeaſon, is for men
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110987:19"/>by fraud and force to worke out their owne ends.</p>
            <p>When you have done with the authour,
<note place="margin">The right of Presbyteries is divine, not humane only.</note> you turn your ſelfe to two other ſorts of men, firſt to theſe who preſſe Presbyterian Diſcipline upon a meere humane right; who theſe are I doe not know, if any ſuch be, it ſeems they are more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate then your verie ſelf, and many others of the Prelaticall faction, who dare not now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, what ever before was their language, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of the Presbyterie, that the principall members thereof, the preaching Presbyters, are inveſted by God with the power of Ordination, and Juriſdiction, though the Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> ever ſince the Reformation, have ſpoiled them of their due, and kept them in ſlaverie, as much altogether if not more, as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Biſhops doe their inferiour ſlaves of the Clergie this day.</p>
            <p>The two conſiderations you bring to beare off theſe men are both impertinent,
<note place="margin">Your plea for keeping up of Biſhops, is the very ſame which the Papiſts uſed againſt King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, for the upholding of the Pope and Monks.</note> The firſt was preſſed with much more acuracie and eloquence, then you, or any of your partie can uſe, by <hi>More</hi> the Chancelor, and the Cardinall of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eighth; it was the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie and paſſionate declamation of theſe men, that the Popes authoritie was ever reverenced in <hi>England,</hi> ſince it was Chriſtian, That for many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it had been confirmed, by numbers of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, That Abbots and Priors were a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of the Parliament, at leaſt foure
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110987:20"/>times more then Biſhops, That Monkes, Fryers, and Nuns had been eſtabliſhed in all times, in all places, That the caſting out of theſe would be a change exceeding dangerous for the State, That the keeping of the things with the removall of the abuſes would be a reformation ſatisfactory to all reaſonable complainers. This here is your moſt ſpecious plea anſwered long agoe by the actions of King <hi>Henry,</hi> King <hi>Edward,</hi> Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to uſe now any verball reply were but ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p>What you ſpeake of the great learning of your Biſhops, ſuppone it to be true, yet you are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly prejudicate, if you ſee not as much if not more of that quality in far mo of the Engliſh Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines who never were Biſhops, theſe few whoſe eminencies hath kythed in the epiſcopall charge might have advanced further, as themſelves will confeſſe, both in learning and pietie, if they never had beene burthened with Epiſcopall diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Your gloriation of the honour done by ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to your Divines wee doe not envie, only we conceive you miſtaken, when you apply the reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects done to the fame of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> unto the perſons of the Biſhops, let bee to their Epiſcopacie, what ever reſpect that gratious Kirk has gotten from any ſtranger, we believe it might have been multiplied if their Biſhops had long ago bin aboliſhed, for they &amp; their tail hath beene allways the onely ſubject of feare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110987:20"/>of the full and plenary affections of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Churches towards their Siſter of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Your ſelves are forc'd to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree unto all the confidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble changes that are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite.</note> To fall out upon that Common place of changes in Church or State, it doth not well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you, ſince both your ſelfe, and all theſe of your Prelates, who would be conceived to have any ſponke, either of pietie, wiſdome, or mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, doe willingly conſent to the far greateſt part of the change, whereby you would affright the State at this time; for your ſelfe along all this Treatiſe, and the prime of your Prelates, in the draughts of Government that come from their hands, ſeem to acknowledge the neceſſitie of erecting Presbyteries over all the Land, and pulling at laſt from the Biſhops, the power of Ordination and Juriſdiction, which too long they have unjuſtly poſſeſſed, that therewith the Presbyteries and Synods may bee inveſted, to whom by Divine Right they grant it belongs. Further, the putting downe of the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Officiall Courts as meerly abuſive, the removing alſo of all the Clergy from Secular employments, and ſo from the Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What more is petitioned, will not intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any farther change, either of cuſtome or Laws, that is conſiderable; while therefore your ſelfe doe offer to begin, or at leaſt to goe on with the far greateſt part of the change, you ought not to be heard in oppoſing ſome farther Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then you can agree to upon the pretended dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of alteration.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:110987:21"/>
            <p>Your other conſideration is leſſe pertinent to the purpoſe,
<note place="margin">The world has had too long and too heavie experience of the ungracious fruits of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacie.</note> but more injurious to your profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed modeſty, your prudence here is not ruled by reaſon, while you adviſe the holding out of the required diſcipline for ſome yeers, till by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience you have ſeene the fruits of it amongſt your neighbours; is not the experience of twice forty yeeres and above, which many places have felt both of the Presbvteriall and Epiſcopall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, more then ſufficient? in all the reformed Churches wee ſee powred out upon the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery by the hand of God, the firſt author of it, plentifull bleſſings, Wee ſee Epiſcopacie curſed in every ſoile it commeth with very bad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, in the Romiſh Churches this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the powerfull inſtrument of Satan to bar out the light of the Goſpel, in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> wee have ſeene grow upon it the Aples of ſtrife, ſuperſtition, pride, and many other evils, till of late it did become the horſe, whereupon came poaſting to the whole Iſle, Arminianiſme, Popery, and a bloudy warre for the hazard of the lives, eſtates, liberties, and all that was dear to any man, if the miraculous hand of God had not caſt the Horſe &amp; his rider in the ditch of his vengeance; thoſe that would wait any longer to get any further experience of the fruits of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie may in juſtice meete with the miſchiefs which ordinarily fall upon them who tempt the Almighty.</p>
            <p>What you ſpeake of the unquietneſſe of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110987:21"/>Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the time of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian diſcipline, it is far beyond the truth, never Church more quiet and free from inward divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions then that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the beginning to this houre, except ſo far as this unhappie inſtrument of Epiſcopacie did creat them trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Your boaſting of ſo great Pietie and vertue of thoſe plants who have grown under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of your government needes not any anſwer.</p>
            <p>Compariſons are odious, where <hi>England</hi> had ever one gratious Plant, wee wiſh it had beene multiplied to a 1000, yet wee muſt be permitted to think that the goodneſſe which has appeared in any member of the Engliſh Church has flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from other fountains then that dry one of Epiſcopacie, what grace it hath been the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of, to thoſe who have beene neareſt to its influence, what vertues are moſt conſpicuous in their families, their Cathedralls, their Chaptors, their Courts, the World knowes, If you were ſo wiſe as you pretend, you would have beene ſilent at this time of Epiſcopall fruits; read over the thouſands of petitions that are preſented already to the eyes of this very Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Biſhops, and Preachers, their greateſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, you dare not ſay, if all the crimes that ever were known, let be preſented to any judicato ry, of all the presbyterian Preachers this hundred yeeres were put to gether, that either in number or quality they come neere to the black roule
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110987:22"/>which the regiſters of this own yeere will tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the eares of after ages, of the gratious ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of that your noble plant. Who ſo will take pains to compare the crimes preſented to the Parliaments in the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, againſt the Fryers, Monks, and Nunnes of thoſe times, for which their whole orders were for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver baniſhed the land, with theſe which now are delated of the Biſhops and their faction, Wee believe that the former ſhall be found not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant for the razing of the Abbacies, as the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doe require the pulling up by the roote of that old rotten tree of whoſe fruits you are here boaſting.</p>
            <p>The other kind of men you admoniſh are a multitude of your brethren in the Prelaticall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<note place="margin">Your reproof of theſe crying abominations whereof you confeſſe the Prelats to be guilty is both cold and ſhort.</note> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſay are too obſtinate in retaining what ever hath beene eſtabliſhed; your advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them is calme, modeſt, &amp; ſhort enough, it is but in ſome few particulars (and that with the clauſe of a perhaps) wherein the generall and conſtant clamour againſt them, you confeſſe, is juſtifiable and ought to bee heard. How faintly and coldly touch you upon theſe evills which your conſcience doth know to be crying abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and to have beene long committed with an high hand? you name but too few; their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the fourth Command: of the Morall Law, their turning of all the pietie of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, into a number of Legall, and Popiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, their contempt of Souls for the love of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110987:22"/>money, in a world of Pluraliſts, and Non-Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, their mixing of Heaven and Earth, Chriſt and the World, in joyning to the burthen of their ſpirituall charge, the load of all the temporall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices which by any means they can attain, they teach, that the Biſhop is the only proper Paſtor of his whole Dioceſſe, to whom alone the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and moſt proper care of all the ſouls in that great flock doth belong, and yet as if it were not enough to charge one poore man with the cure of ſome five or ſix hundred thouſand perſons, yea of ſome forty or fifty hundred thouſand, for readily the dioceſſe of <hi>Lincolne</hi> will exceed the firſt number, and that of <hi>London</hi> the ſecond, as if all theſe brought not burthen enough to the ſhoulders of one man, The weight of the great Seal and of the white ſtaff, the greateſt temporall offices in the Kingdome, muſt be joyned thereto, that the cenſure of the Church ſhould be reſt, againſt all Law Divine, and humane, out of the hands of Preachers, &amp; caſt on the rabble of your Laick Canoniſts, that they by their Courts may make havock of the goods and perſons of the whole Nation, In all theſe you doe well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your ſinne in fighting againſt the voice of God, in your impudent outfacing, and obſtinate reſiſting the cleere light of all reaſon; here it was indeed where your pen would have beene a little more pungent, for you know, you have to do with an hard hearted generation of men, who minde reformation in nothing if they bee not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110987:23"/>compelled; as every pin of their Tabernacle, and the whole frame of their government, is brought from the Mountains of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo that principall maxime of Popiſh policie, that the Church muſt not be conceived by People ever to have erred, is the chiefe ſquare, and great rule, according to the which hetherto they have ruled all their adminiſtrations, to think of a reformation in any thing were to give grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the adverſaries, were the beginning of a declination, they ſee a deep precipice before them, if once they bee put to a mooving they know not where the reſt and period of their diſcent may be, ſo by all meanes, the preſent ſtation muſt bee kept without the yielding willingly of one foot of ground.
<note place="margin">No Prelate can be excuſed of great guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Have not theſe ſpirituall Lords ſitten already above 4. moneths in the convocation and Parliament? have any of them to this day made the leaſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſtop the courſe of thoſe hereſies and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries which to their certain knowledg have bin theſe yeers paſt like a gangreene, like a peſt, like a firie poiſon infecting ſouls over all the Land? Should any reaſonable men ever more take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of any their motions? can ever any faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be expected from them who ſo manifeſtly have betrayed the truſt which the King and the Country did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit to them, of their religion, and ſouls? no thanks to them, that <hi>Canterbury</hi> long ere now had not ſo firmly rooted Arminianiſme and Popery in the Church, with a tyrannous oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the ſtate, as we and our poſteritie had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110987:23"/>beene able in any after age to have gotten it amended. It is eaſie to diſcern what ſpirit hee is, who moves men to be clamorouſly contentious, when the queſtion commeth to any matter of their own dignitie, their own rents, their own ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonious toys, but to be dumbe like fiſh, when before their eyes, the doctrine, the worſhip, the Saints of God, are moſt miſerably trampled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the foule feet of moſt inſolent men. Thoſe of the Prelats who count themſelves moſt ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, and innocent, cannot be excuſed of theſe crimes, which by their connivence they did fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and well neere as much promove by their ſuffering,
<note place="margin">The World upon good grounds, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects from this Parliament, the abolition of Epiſcopacie.</note> as the other who were eſteemed more guiltie by their doings; who ſo will be pleaſed to make an accurate ſearch by what meanes the Prince of darkneſſe did moſt enable the one, I mean the <hi>Canterburian</hi> Prelats, to be ſo active and ſucceſsfull in their evill deſigne, and by what means the other who ſtill in private did profeſſe their diſaffection from theſe ways, were ſubdued to be ſo paſſive and ſilent, when errour, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and oppreſsion, in the Church were advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing with ſuch ſpeed before their face, Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie will be found the inſtrument which cloſed the mouth, and tied the hands of the one from ſpeaking or doing thoſe things which the honour of God, and welfare of the Church, then ſo deeply wounded, did require, but opened the mouth, and ſtrengthened the hand of the other, for ſaying and doing what ever they found con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceable
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110987:24"/>for their miſchievous ends. How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and glorious a work would it be for this gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Parliament, to adde as a Crown and Coap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to all the bleſsings which the Church and State hath felt already, and yet expects from their hands, the breaking in pieces of this unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie inſtrument, which in the hands of evill men is a very ſharp ſword, and firebrand, for executing of all their furious follies, and in the hand of good men becometh a bond of braſſe or ſteel, for binding them up from thoſe good words and works, which the World would certainly have expected from them, if they had beene free of ſuch ſlaviſh fetters?</p>
            <p>If it might bee the will of God to move the minds of the Houſe of Commons, to behold the teares, the ſighes, the prayers, which for many yeeres numbers of godly ſouls have been pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out before God and men, from their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie ſenſe of the cruell oppreſsion, ſpirituall and temporall, of the hierarchie, to read with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsionate eye the ſupplications, which from the hands and hearts of many thouſands, in all the corners of the Kingdome, are come already, and daily encreaſe againſt that root of all their woe: to looke vpon the reſpectfull faces of all the Reformed Churches who at this inſtant of time with more paſsionate deſires, with a greater meaſure of hope then ever before, are greedily gazing to behold, if now at laſt, that great ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke and ſole impediment of a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110987:24"/>amongſt all the gracious Siſters can be gotten removed, and caſt into the Sea. But above all, to blenke up and fix their thoughts upon that great God, who but juſt now, here ſaved them all from ſo horrible a danger, and in the midſt of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, has lifted up to them an enſigne of the faireſt hopes; Unto that God, who daily walks in the midſt of theſe Honourable Houſes, which he alone has both aſſembled and kept thus long together above the thoughts of all men, whether friends or foes, expecting by way of thankfulnes from thoſe who deſire to bee counted faithfull ſervants, either to him or their Countrey, a full reſolution to govern themſelves in the affaires of his Houſe, eſpecially this great one which ſo neerly concernes his honour, by his ſole plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, without any regard of worldly midſes, or baſe ends, which may draw them away one haires breadth from his Majeſties direction: If it may be the good pleaſure of the Lord to ſettle ſuch thoughts in the hearts of the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, they are few who make queſtion, but by their means, the higher houſe of the Peeres may be induced, as in all things elſe, ſo in this, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre in a joint ſupplication towards our gratious Soveraigne, that by the ſtrength of their threefold cord, they may pul up that old bitter root, which ſo long hath beene noxious to the ſoile, both of the Church and State.</p>
            <p>If otherwayes the thoughts of the lower houſe ſhould be diverted from theſe and the like
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110987:25"/>conſiderations, if they ſhould faint and give over to proſecute with courage, with faith, and hope, this truly noble deſigne, they would do well to forethink, unto whom after ages will impute all the inconveniences which readily may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to the King, to the Countrey, to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches abroad, by this unhappy Epiſcopacie, which if now retained after ſo full an examination of its nature and conſequences in ſo grave and wiſe a Court cannot but take deeper root then ever, &amp; be more firmly eſtabliſhed againſt all poſsibilitie of any future removall. What ever the events hereof may prove, our Gracious Sovereigne, and higher Houſe of Parliament, may not ſo well be charged therewith, they having given ſo many late documents of their great readineſſe to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto all the equitable motions, though never ſo full of difficulties at the firſt appearance, which the Houſe of Commons with any unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and earneſtneſſe have as yet proponed: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, it is to that Houſe alone, unto which the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous petitions demonſtrating, not only the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of the men, but the inherent and eſſentiall corruptions of the office hath been preſented: It is the ſtate of Commons that moſt have taſted of Epiſcopacies bitterfruits, It is the Commons of the Land who will moſt be beaten, if Biſhops remain with their paſtorall rod, who moſt will be trod upon by the feet of their pride, and ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the violence of their rapacious hands. To this Houſe therefore, above all others, ſince
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110987:25"/>for this once, God has put in their hand to may, if they will, ſhall be aſcribed either the un-uttera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grief of the Godly, for retaining, or their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable joy, for utter aboliſhing all degrees of Epiſcopacie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle l 19 r. thy. p. 10. l. 3. r. us with. p. 17. l. 2. r. <hi>Gerſem Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous.</hi> p. 25. lin. 23. for that read what.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <head>The Stationer to the buying Reader.</head>
            <p>LOving Reader, bee pleaſed to take notice that the queſtion of Epiſcopacie diſcuſſed from Scripture and Fathers, promiſed upon the title of this Book, was intended by the Reverend Author to be joyned to this Reply, but ſome weighty cauſe having brought this to publike view firſt, and by it ſelfe, I thought good (after the printing of the ſaid title, in ſervice both to him and thee) to give notice of it. I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours <hi>T. V.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
